Tēlemachos Alaveras Papers and Nea Poreia Archives, 1989-2010: Finding Aid C1408
Manuscripts Division
- Series 2: Nea Poreia Archives, 1918-2009; 43 boxes
  - Subseries 2D: Associations-Organizations, 1962-2005; 4 boxes
    - Hidryma Meletōn Chersonēsou tou Haimou [Institute for Balkan Studies], 1972-1974; 1 folder (Box 84, Folder 7)
      Includes correspondence; contracts; autograph and typescript lists of the organization's publications; miscellaneous notes; a sample of a publication; and receipts.
    - Kratiko Theatro Voreiou Hellados (KΘΒΕ) [National Theater of Northern Greece - Ministry of Culture and Tourism], 1970-1973; 2 folders (Box 84, Folder 8-9)
      Includes autograph manuscripts and typescripts of Alaveras's proposals to National Theater of Northern Greece regarding theatrical plays; correspondence; invitations/agendas for board meetings; a bound copy of a report of the proceedings (June 1970-June 1971); and playbills.
    - Logotexniko Arxeio Thessalonikēs [Literary Archive of Thessalonikē], 2001-2002; 2 folders (Box 86, Folder 1-2)
      Includes the by-laws, miscellaneous documents, and correspondence with the Greek Ministry of Culture.
    - Syllogos Apophoitōn Peiramatikou Scholeiou Aristoteleiou Panepistēmiou Thessalonikēs [Experimental School of Aristotle University of Thessaloniki], 1973-1983; 2 folders (Box 86, Folder 3-4)
      Includes autograph and typescript drafts, as well as page proofs of an edition regarding the history of the Experimental School.
    - Vaphopouleion Cultural Center, Thessalonikē (Greece), 1991-1999; 3 folders (Box 86, Folder 5-7)
      Includes printed invitations, brochures, the program of the exhibition, the publications of Nea Poreia (1955-1992), and the roundtable discussion (January 29, 1992) that took place at the Vaphopouleion Cultural Center. There is an autograph manuscript of Michalēs Meraklēs's presentation and Alaveras's miscellaneous notes. Included also are plans of the exhibition gallery; posters; the captions of the items; and color photographs.
  - Subseries 2E: Miscellaneous Documents: Legal; Financial; Contact Information; Press; Memorabilia, 1951-2007; 3 boxes
    This subseries consists of miscellaneous material, such as financial, administrative, legal, contact information, and papers by school or college students.
    This subseries has been organized by type of material.
    - Legal, 1951-2007; 1 box
      - Hellenic Association of Press Directors, 1951-1958; 1 folder (Box 86, Folder 8)
      - Insurance Fund Owners, Editors, and Press Officers, 1960-1964; 1 folder (Box 86, Folder 9)
      - Lease and Private Agreements; Certificates, 1955-2007; 1 folder (Box 86, Folder 10)
      - Administrative and Other Material, 1961-1979; 1 folder (Box 86, Folder 11)
        Includes incoming correspondence from several organizations and governmental offices regarding their subscription or the order of Nea Poreia, as well as their mutual collaboration.
      - International Standard Book Number (ISBN), 1996-2006; 1 folder (Box 86, Folder 12)
    - Financial, 1958-2007; 2 boxes
      - Tax-Exempt Papers, 1971-1988; 1 folder (Box 86, Folder 13)
      - Receipt Books, 1959-1986; 1 folder (Box 86, Folder 14)
      - Receipt Books, undated; 1 folder (Box 87, Folder 1)
      - Receipts, 1958-1996; 2 folders (Box 87, Folder 2-3)
      - Budget Expenses; Acknowledgements, 1969-2002; 1 folder (Box 87, Folder 4)
      - Expense Book and Invoices, 1959-2007; 1 folder (Box 87, Folder 5)
      - Bills; Claims; Subscriptions, 1966-2007; 1 folder (Box 87, Folder 6)
      - Proposal for Printing Services, 1992; 1 folder (Box 87, Folder 7)
        Includes proposal instructions for the printing of the book Mesaiōnike ephyalōmenē kerameikē tēs Kyprou and an undated signed private agreement.
    - Contact Information, 1956-1996; 1 box
      - Mailing Lists, 1995-1996; 2 folders (Box 87, Folder 8-9)
      - Address Books, 1956-1970; 2 folders (Box 87, Folder 10-11)
    - Press, 1980-1981; 1 box
      - Press Releases, AMss & TMss, undated; 1 folder (Box 88, Folder 1)
      - Radio Broadcasts, 1980-1981; 1 folder (Box 88, Folder 2)
    - List of Greek literary works, 1976-1977; 1 folder (Box 88, Folder 3)
    - Memorabilia, undated; 2 folders (Box 88, Folder 4-5)
      Includes seals of Nea Poreia and metal plates with Alavaeras's name on them.
  - Subseries 2F: Printed Material, 1953-2009; 3 boxes
    Includes originals and photocopies of clippings of several Greek and some foreign newspapers and magazines regarding Nea Poreia and other literary topics.
    This subseries has been organized primarily by type of material and secondly in a chronological order.
    - Transparencies, undated; 1 folder (Box 88, Folder 6)
    - Offprints, 1969-1979; 1 folder (Box 88, Folder 7)
    - Charē Patsē, Nea Hellēnikē Enkyklopaideia, 11; 155-158, undated; 1 folder (Box 88, Folder 8)
    - Domē, 137-138, 1970; 1 folder (Box 88, Folder 8)
    - Ephēmeris tēs Kyvernēseōs, 1953-1974; 1 folder (Box 88, Folder 9)
      Included are the follwoing issues: 93 (16 Apr. 1953) and 130 (27 Aug. 1963), as well as photocopies of the first and second volumes dated 1973 and 1974.
    - Exōstēs, 76, 1989 December 22; 1 folder (Box 88, Folder 9)
    - Hē Chōra, 1924 June 7; 1 folder (Box 88, Folder 9)
    - Hē Ephēmerida tōn Poiētōn, 19, 1958 June-July; 1 folder (Box 88, Folder 9)
    - Het Antenneke, 7, 1956 January-March; 1 folder (Box 88, Folder 9)
    - Korax, 1, 5, 6, undated; 1 folder (Box 88, Folder 9)
    - Logotechnikē Enkyklopaideia, 18, undated; 1 folder (Box 88, Folder 9)
    - Logotechniko Deltio, 56 & 114, 1977 June; 1 folder (Box 88, Folder 9)
    - Nees Idees, 231, 1996 April 4; 1 folder (Box 88, Folder 9)
    - Swiat literacki, 5/92, undated; 1 folder (Box 88, Folder 9)
    - Panathēnaia, 4, 1959 April; 1 folder (Box 88, Folder 9)
    - Covers of Nea Poreia editions, 1980-1985; 1 folder (Box 89, Folder 1)
    - Brochures; Invitations; Programs, 1972-2001; 2 folders (Box 89, Folder 2-3)
    - Posters, 1974-1992; 1 folder (Box 89, Folder 4)
    - Newspaper and Magazines Clippings, 1953-1971; 1 folder (Box 89, Folder 5)
      Includes clippings of several Greek newspapers regarding the publications of Nea Poreia.
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1972-1989; 1 folder (Box 89, Folder 6)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1990-1999; 1 folder (Box 89, Folder 7)
      Includes clippings of several Greek newspapers and literary magazines regarding cultural activities, new publications, interviews, and announcements that took place in Thessalonikē and in general in Greece or abroad.
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1992-2002; 1 folder (Box 89, Folder 8)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1998-2007; 1 folder (Box 90, Folder 1)
      Includes clippings exclusively on Nea Poreia and one issue of the newspaper magazine Vivliothēkē, 317 (July 23, 2004).
    - Newspaper Clippings, 2004-2009; 1 folder (Box 90, Folder 2)
- Series 3: Chrēstos Alaveras Family Papers, 1890-1979; 8 boxes
  This series includes personal papers of Tēlemachos Alaveras's father, Chrēstos Alaveras.
  This series has been organized in three subseries: A. Correspondence; B. Documents; and C. Photographs.
  - Subseries 3A: Correspondence, 1907-1979; 2 boxes
    This subseries consists of incoming and outgoing correspondence among close relatives or friends of Chrēstos Alaveras.
    - Alaveras, Apostolos, 1914; 1 folder (Box 90, Folder 3)
      Includes outgoing correspondence to Tēlemachos Alaveras.
    - Alaveras, Chrēstos and Aikaterinē, 1927-1934; 1 folder (Box 90, Folder 4)
      Includes correspondecne between Aikaterinē (Katina) and Chrēstos Alaveras (parents of Tēlemachos Alaveras).
    - Alaveras, Chrēstos, 1907-1950; 1 folder (Box 90, Folder 5)
      Includes incoming and outgoing corrsepondence with Chrēstos Alaveras's siblings, the Archimandritēs Phōtios of Philippopolis (Bulgaria), and acquaintances.
    - Alaveras, Dēmētrios, 1920-1935; 1 folder (Box 90, Folder 6)
      Includes incoming and outgoing correspondence among close family members and friends, with his brother Chrēstos Alaveras, his sister Pēnelopē, with Charalampos Varympopēs, and one letter to an unidentified recipient.
    - Giarikē, Pēnelopē, 1920-1940; 1 folder (Box 90, Folder 7)
      Includes incoming and outgoing correspondence between Pēnelope Giarikē and her brother Chrēstos Alaveras. There are also two letters from Pēnelopē to Katina (Aikaterinē) Alavera.
    - Kakridēs, Geōrgios and Charikleia, 1913-1956; 2 folders (Box 90, Folder 8-9)
      Includes incoming and outgoing correspondence mostly with Chrēstos and Katina (Aikaterinē) Alaveras and with Tēlemachos and Dēmētrios Alaveras. There is also a letter from Charikleia to her son, Andreas; one letter from Geōrgios Kakridēs to Katina Alavera; one letter from Pēnelope Giarikē; two letters from Charikleia to her nephew, Tēlemachos Alaveras; and one letter from Tēlemachos to his uncle Geōrgios.
    - Keroglou, Maria and Chrysaphoglou, Kalliroē, 1925-1927; 1 folder (Box 91, Folder 1)
    - Mezevirēs, Kōnstantinos A. and Stephanos, 1907-1915; 1 folder (Box 91, Folder 2)
      Includes incoming and outgoing correspondence with Chrēstos and Vasilikē Alaveras (Mezevirēs's sister).
    - Tsoukalas, Geōrgios and Koula, 1926-1979; 2 folders (Box 91, Folder 3-4)
      Includes a bound volume containing carbon copies of Geōrgios Tsoukalas's letters to relatives and acquaintances both in Greek and French dated 1927-1929, as well as original outgoing correspondence from both Geōrgios and Koula Tsoukalas (1927-1979).
    - Miscellaneous and Unidentified, 1908-1959; 2 folders (Box 91, Folder 5-6)
      Includes correspondence from Agēsilaos Alaveras to his father (one letter); from Charikleia Kakridē to Maria (unidentified); from aunt Helenē (unidentified) to Katina (Aikaterinē) Alaveras; from Geōrgios N. Chatzidakis; from Kōnstantinos Boukouras; from Marika Pappa; from Georges I. Kyrou. There is also one folder of correspondence mostly in Bulgarian and French. Additionally, there are many empty envelopes.
  - Subseries 3B: Documents, 1896-1977; 6 boxes
    This subseries consists of personal documents of Chrēstos Alaveras's family.
    - Accounts, 1912-1931; 2 folders (Box 91, Folder 7-8)
    - Account Books, 1913-1937; 1 folder (Box 92, Folder 1)
      Includes loose pages of notebooks, one bound, and one teared containing detailed personal accounts of Chrēstos Alaveras in Bulgaria.
    - Account Books, 1915-1929; 2 folders (Box 92, Folder 2-3)
      Includes three notebooks of Chrēstos Alaveras containing daily accounts of his family expenses in Greek and a few receipts in Bulgarian, as well as other information pertinent to his business mostly with family members.
    - Account Books, 1924-1937; 2 folders (Box 92, Folder 4-5)
    - Financial and Legal Documents, 1896-1925; 1 folder (Box 92, Folder 6)
      Includes miscellaneous financial and other legal documents of Chrēstos Alaveras mostly in Bulgarian and some in Greek; there is also correspondence with his brother Geōrgios regarding their father's property; one letter from his sister, Pēnelopē; and a few letters from acquaintances pertinent to business in Greek. (Tēlemachos Alaveras's note on the discarded envelope stated that these documents are from Bulgaria).
    - Financial (Bulgaria case), 1912-1926; 1 folder (Box 92, Folder 7)
      Includes notebooks of daily expenses. Note by Tēlemachos Alaveras on the discarded envelope stated that this material contains information about a case in Bulgaria.
    - Financial (Bulgaria case), 1930-1933; 2 folders (Box 93, Folder 1-2)
    - Financial, 1923-1930; 2 folders (Box 93, Folder 3-4)
    - Miscellaneous Documents in Bulgarian, 1913-1925; 2 folders (Box 93, Folder 5-6)
      Includes several documents in Bulgarian.
    - Miscellaneous Documents, 1909-1948; 1 folder (Box 93, Folder 7)
      Includes documents of Chrēstos Alaveras in Bulgarian. Handwritten note by Tēlemachos Alaveras explains that the content of this folder was submitted to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs by Chrēstos on October 8, 1948. Included is the receipt of the application and a handwritten note by Chrēstos Alaveras.
    - Contracts, 1897-1924; 1 folder (Box 94, Folder 1)
      Includes several documents regarding family assets and marriage contracts of Alaveras's family. The documents are written mostly in Bulgarian and Greek and a few in French.
    - Lease Agreement and Receipts, 1928-1930; 2 folders (Box 94, Folder 2-3)
      Includes apartment lease agreements by Chrēstos Alaveras and handwritten receipts in Greek.
    - Claims, 1926-1931; 1 folder (Box 94, Folder 4)
      Includes a notebook, loose pages, and correspondence with the advocat, George Kyrou, regarding claiming issues.
    - Committee for Emigration of Minorities between Greece and Bulgaria, 1924-1940; 1 folder (Box 94, Folder 5)
    - Certificat de membre de minorite ethnique; Declaration d'Emigration; Lettre de voiture, 1913-1927; 1 folder (Box 94, Folder 6)
    - Passports, 1908-1914; 1 folder (Box 94, Folder 7)
    - Heridetary, 1925-1954; 1 folder (Box 94, Folder 8)
    - Divorce Petition and Other Documents, 1924-1933; 1 folder (Box 94, Folder 9)
      Includes the original documents of the divorce petition that Katina (Aikaterinē Tsoukala) Alavera filed for the dissolution of her marriage with Chrēstos Alaveras. There are also handwritten original copies of the birth certificate and baptism of Tēlemachos Alaveras; receipts of tuition payment for the elementary school for Tēlemachos and handwritten notes on the expenses. There is also the individual health booklet of Chrēstos.
    - Greek Educational Association Stenēmachou (members list), 1910-1920; 1 folder (Box 94, Folder 10)
    - Ergolavia Limenikōn Ergōn Thessalonikēs (ER-ThA), 1938-1948; 1 folder (Box 95, Folder 1)
    - Voting cards; power of attorney, 1921-1950; 1 folder (Box 95, Folder 2)
    - Birth certificate; school transcript; and applications, 1891-1938; 1 folder (Box 95, Folder 3)
    - Legal case, 1930-1931; 1 folder (Box 95, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous Material, 1909-1952; 8 folders (Box 95, Folder 5-12)
      Included are miscellaneous financial and other legal documents, notebooks, and notes written mostly in Bulgarian, in Greek, and some in French.
    - Geōrgios Tsoukalas Documents, 1844-1996; 1 folder (Box 95, Folder 13)
    - Aikaternē Tsoukala-Alavera Documents, 1929-1977; 1 box
      - Notebook, 1938; 1 folder (Box 96, Folder 1)
        Includes a notebook of Alaveras's mother written in French and loose pages both in Greek and in French.
      - Diary, 1977; 1 folder (Box 96, Folder 2)
        Includes a notebook written by Aikaterinē Tsoukala containing autograph manuscript drafts regarding her genealogical tree. It is entitled: "Katerinē Tsoukala. To oikogeneiako mas dendro. 1977."
      - Will of Aikaterinē Tsoukala-Alavera, 2004; 1 folder (Box 96, Folder 3)
      - Miscellaneous documents, 1919-1982; 1 folder (Box 96, Folder 4)
        Includes miscellaneous legal and medical documents, her identification card, and notes.
  - Subseries 3C: Photographs, 1890-1982; 2 boxes
    This subseries consists of Chrēstos Alavera family photographs.
    This subseries has been organized approximately in a chronological order.
    - Chrēstos Alaveras and Charikleia Alavera Kakridē, 1890; 1 folder (Box 96, Folder 5)
    - Alaveras's Family, 1911-1982; 1 folder (Box 96, Folder 6)
    - Tsoukalas' Family, 1911-1919; 1 folder (Box 96, Folder 7)
    - Unidentified Group Portraits, undated; 1 box (Box 97)
    - Unidentified, 1936; 1 folder (Box 96, Folder 8)
    - Postcards, undated; 1 folder (Box 96, Folder 9)